Guide to the Arthur Kornberg Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
- Profiles in Science images and metadata, 2007 Sep 14; Accession ARCH-2007-322; 400 megabyte(s); (321 computer files in 4 directories)
  - Letter from Muriel Beadle to Arthur Kornberg, 1/26/1965; WHBBGR; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    In 1966, geneticist and Nobel laureate George Beadle and his wife Muriel published a laymen's guide to genetics titled "The Language of Life: An Introduction to the Science of Genetics." In this 1965 letter, Muriel Beadle asked Kornberg to clarify some details of his DNA synthesis work to include in the book.
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg to Muriel Beadle, 2/4/1965; WHBBGS; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    In 1966, geneticist and Nobel laureate George Beadle and his wife Muriel published a laymen's guide to genetics titled "The Language of Life: An Introduction to the Science of Genetics." In this 1965 letter, Kornberg responded to Muriel Beadle's request for details of his DNA synthesis work to include in the book.
  - Letter from Muriel Beadle to Arthur Kornberg, 2/14/1965; WHBBGT; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    In 1966, geneticist and Nobel laureate George Beadle and his wife Muriel published a laymen's guide to genetics titled "The Language of Life: An Introduction to the Science of Genetics." In an earlier letter, Muriel Beadle had asked Kornberg to clarify some details of his DNA synthesis work to include in the book. In this letter, she attached a chapter draft incorporating his response.; Item is handwritten.
  - [Chapter 19, p. 219], circa Feb 1965; WHBBGV; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Muriel Beadle sent Kornberg this manuscript insert for Chapter 19 of "The Language of Life: An Introduction to the Science of Genetics," after incorporating some details on his DNA synthesis work. Co-authored by geneticist George Beadle, the book was published in 1966.
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg to D. S. Fahrney, 1/14/1965; WHBBGW; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Like many acclaimed scientists, Kornberg was keenly aware that scientific merit was not the sole basis for awards and other honors. He made this clear when asked to recommend others for awards, as in this letter regarding Marshall Nirenberg, who would win a Nobel Prize in 1968 for his work on the genetic code.
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg to Allan Hauck, 5/27/1965; WHBBGY; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    As a Nobel laureate, Kornberg often received requests for his opinions on philosophical questions. He responded with concise and thoughtful answers, as illustrated by his letter to philosophy professor Allan Hauck.
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg to Robert L. Sinsheimer, 7/9/1965; WHBBGZ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Working to synthesize a viable DNA, Kornberg turned to the small bacterial viruses M13 and Phi X174. Biophysicist Robert Sinsheimer at the California Institute of Technology had found that the single-stranded, circular Phi X174 virus DNA was converted to a double helix after entering its E. coli host, and the double stranded form was by itself infective. In this letter, Kornberg asked for a sample of Sinsheimer's virus to start investigating its possible use as a replication template. It was from this virus that Kornberg was able to create an infective synthetic viral DNA in 1967.
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg to Robert L. Sinsheimer, 7/29/1965; WHBBHB; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Working to synthesize a viable DNA, Kornberg turned to the small bacterial viruses M13 and Phi X174. Biophysicist Robert Sinsheimer at the California Institute of Technology had found that the single-stranded, circular Phi X174 virus DNA was converted to a double helix after entering its E. coli host, and by itself was infective. In a previous letter, Kornberg had asked for a sample of Sinsheimer's virus to start investigating its possible use as a replication template. This letter reported on his initial results with the virus. It was from this virus that Kornberg was able to create an infective synthetic viral DNA in 1967.
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg to Henry M. Sobell, 4/22/1965; WHBBHC; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    In their work with DNA polymerase, Kornberg and his colleagues had found that it could induce a seemingly spontaneous synthesis of an adenine-thymine polymer, without a template. This phenomenon raised a number of questions about the nature of chemical bonds in nucleotides and nucleic acids, and the exact mechanism of the polymerase. In this letter, Kornberg responded to Henry Sobell's research proposal on this topic.
  - Letter from Henry M. Sobell to Arthur Kornberg, 12/31/1964; WHBBHD; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    In their work with DNA polymerase, Kornberg and his colleagues had found that it could induce a seemingly spontaneous synthesis of an adenine-thymine polymer, without a template. This phenomenon raised a number of questions about the nature of chemical bonds in nucleotides and nucleic acids, and the exact mechanism of the polymerase. In this letter, Henry Sobell asked Kornberg about the feasibility of approaching some of these problems via crystallographic studies and included his research proposal on this topic.
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg to George Streisinger, 2/2/1965; WHBBHF; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Geneticist George Streisinger was a noted expert on the bacterial virus (phage) T4. In this letter, Kornberg asked him if there might be a mutant strain of T4 suitable for studying DNA synthesis in infected E. coli cells, noting that regular T4 produced so much lysozyme that the host cells were too fragile to harvest.
  - Letter from George Streisinger to Arthur Kornberg, 2/9/1965; WHBBHG; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Geneticist George Streisinger was a noted expert on the bacterial virus (phage) T4, and Kornberg had written to ask him if there might be a mutant strain of T4 suitable for studying DNA synthesis in infected E. coli cells. In this letter, Streisinger explained that such a mutant had been isolated and provided detailed instructions for preparing cultures.
  - The Chemical Basis of Heredity, 10/17/1961; WHBBHH; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    In this lecture given to an audience of non-scientists, Kornberg demonstrated his talent for making complex topics accessible, and provided a look at the state of the art in molecular biology in 1961.
  - [National Cancer Conference presentation (Philadelphia)], 1964-9; WHBBHJ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    In this presentation at the 1964 National Cancer Conference, Kornberg discussed how molecular biology research, though a "poverty pocket" in the academic world, might soon improve our knowledge of how genes function, and how things go wrong in genetic processes.
  - An Understanding of Life on a Molecular Basis, 4-Feb-65; WHBBHL; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    In 1965, Kornberg participated in a lecture series titled "Science--A Challenge to Man's Faith." His presentation discussed the current state of scientific knowledge about inheritance and evolution, the evolution of scientific thought itself, and the role of science as a guide to behavior. Finally, he reflected on the spiritual aspects of the pursuit of knowledge.
  - Basic Motives of a Professional Life, 1969-7; WHBBHN; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Kornberg was trained as a physician before he found his calling in biochemistry, and remained close to medical schools and medical problems throughout his career. In this article, he reflected on three basic motives of a professional life, as applied to careers in medicine and science.
  - Ebb Tide in Medical Research, 9/22/1970; WHBBHP; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    As a researcher who experienced firsthand the immense growth of federal support for scientific research after 1940, Kornberg was troubled by deep research budget cuts during the Nixon administration. As he noted in this essay, scientific research was increasingly important to society, but like anything else, needed advocates to keep the public--and their representatives in government--aware of its value.; Based on remarks made at the Markle Scholars' Meeting.
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg and David S. Hogness to Newton Steward, 10/23/1972; WHBBHQ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    During the 1960s, the California State Department of Education had been increasingly pressured by religious groups to include Creation Theory in science textbooks used in the public schools. In 1972, Kornberg and his colleague David Hogness asked to address the Department on this matter, and explained why they believed that including Creation Theory would be bad for science education (and would make Californians the "laughing stock of the entire civilized world"). After hearings in 1972, the Department of Education decided not to require Creation Theory in science textbooks or curricula.; Item is a photocopy.
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg to Edward Dempsey, 10/30/1956; WHBBHR; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg to Salvador E. Luria, 3/14/1961; WHBBHT; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Arthur Kornberg to Avram Goldstein, 7/16/1957; WHBBMN; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Lab notebook 33, 1957-1958 (excerpt 1)], 30 August - 18 September 1957; WHBBMP; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Item is handwritten. Item is a photocopy.
  - [Lab notebook 33, 1957-1958 (excerpt 2)], 20 September - 1 October 1957; WHBBMQ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Lab notebook 28, 1956 (excerpt 1)], 18-20 July 1956; WHBBMR; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Lab notebook 28, 1956 (excerpt 2)], 30-Aug-56; WHBBMS; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Lab notebook 28, 1956 (excerpt 3)], 6-7 September 1956; WHBBMT; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Lab notebook 28, 1956 (excerpt 4)], 22-25 September 1956; WHBBMV; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Lab notebook 28, 1956 (excerpt 5)], 19-Sep-56; WHBBMW; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Lab notebook 28, 1956 (excerpt 6)], 4-8 October 1956; WHBBMX; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Lab notes on Morton DNA], 6/13/1961; WHBBMZ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from W. E. Cohn to Arthur Kornberg, 3/15/1951; WHBBBW; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Biochemist Waldo Cohn had taught Kornberg the powerful technique of ion exchange chromatography in 1949. In this letter, he responded to Kornberg's recent work on the likely configuration of the nucleotides he was then studying.
  - Letter from Senator Edward M. Kennedy to Arthur Kornberg, 1/31/1978; WHBBDP; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Fact sheet on federal research funding], 19-Jan-78; WHBBDQ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Part of a package for participants in Senate hearings on 19 January 1978.
  - Issues to be Addressed by Scientists with Government, 19-Jan-78; WHBBDR; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Goals of the Scientific Delegation, 19-Jan-78; WHBBDS; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Backgrounder on Recombinant DNA Research, 7/20/1977; WHBBDW; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Alexander Rich to Arthur Kornberg, 3/8/1957; WHBBFJ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Hearings on the Human Impact of Advance in Biological Science [Testimony to Senate Subcommittee on Government Research], 3/8/1968; WHBBHM; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    The success of Kornberg and others in creating synthetic copies of DNA and RNA had provoked public concern about the future consequences of genetic engineering, even before recombinant DNA technology was developed in the 1970s. In March 1968, Kornberg and other leading researchers in the field testified before the Senate Subcommittee on Government Research to address these concerns. Kornberg explained the current state of knowledge in molecular biology, the immense potential for medical applications, and the need for much more federal funding for this branch of research.
  - Letter from Joshua Lederberg to Arthur Kornberg, 1/27/1958; WHBBHS; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Severo Ochoa to Arthur Kornberg, 3/29/1949; WHBBBQ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    In this letter, Kornberg's former mentor Severo Ochoa thanked him for a sample of TPN (triphosphopyridine nucleotide) and discussed his ongoing work on citrate synthesis.
  - Letter from Severo Ochoa to Arthur Kornberg, 1/3/1949; WHBBBR; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    In this letter, Kornberg's former mentor Severo Ochoa discussed his current work with biotin and its possible role in metabolism.
  - [Map of Stanford University Campus], circa 1957; WHBBDZ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Architect's model of new Stanford Medical Center], 1957; WHBBFC; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Construction of Edwards Building, Stanford Medical School], circa 1958; WHBBFW; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Construction of hospital wing, Stanford Medical School], circa 1958; WHBBFX; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Construction of Lane Medical Library, Stanford Medical School], circa 1958; WHBBFY; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - [Construction of Clinic Building, Stanford Medical School], circa 1958; WHBBFZ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Severo Ochoa to Arthur Kornberg, 5/11/1962; WHBBGQ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Robert K. Morton to Arthur Kornberg, 11/29/1961; WHBBCB; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Biologists and biochemists during the 1940s and 1950s frequently shared their supplies of enzymes and other products of their labs, as there was often no other source. Here Robert Morton responded to Kornberg's report, sent several weeks earlier.
  - Letter from the editors of the Journal of Biological Chemistry to Arthur Kornberg, 1/24/1958; WHBBCJ; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Francis Crick to Arthur Kornberg, 5/10/1960; WHBBCS; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Andre Lwoff to Arthur Kornberg, 9/27/1960; WHBBCY; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Van R. Potter to Arthur Kornberg, 5/18/1960; WHBBDC; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - DNA Synthesizer Says Fear of Unknown Hurts Research, 9/10/1969; WHBBDT; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Creator of DNA Scores Talk of 'Biological Bomb', 1/6/1972; WHBBDV; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Francis Crick to Arthur Kornberg, 10/17/1959; WHBBGM; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    Writing to congratulate Kornberg on receiving a Nobel Prize, Francis Crick also provided an update on the current work of his colleagues Max Perutz and John Kendrew. In 1962, Perutz and Kendrew would share the Nobel Prize in Chemistry for their work on the structures of proteins such as hemoglobin and myoglobin; Crick would share the Nobel Prize in Medicine or Physiology with James Watson and Maurice Wilkins, for the discovery of the structure of DNA.; Item is handwritten.
  - Letter from Allan Hauck to Arthur Kornberg, 4/27/1965; WHBBGX; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
    As a Nobel laureate, Kornberg often received requests for his opinions on philosophical questions, as illustrated by this letter from philosophy professor Allan Hauck.
  - Letter from Peter M. Brown to Arthur Kornberg, 1/12/1965; WHBBHK; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - Letter from Robert K. Morton to Arthur Kornberg, 7/14/1961; WHBBNB; 1 computer file(s) (TIFF)